Guide to the Farwell Knapp Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Farwell Knapp papers
1891-1947
1907-1942
YCAL MSS 256
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
7.75
(20 boxes)
The Farwell Knapp Papers, largely consisting of correspondence, journals, photographs, and other papers, documents the personal and professional life of Connecticut tax lawyer Farwell Knapp. Knapp's experience as a student at Yale University and Harvard University law school are recorded, including his involvement with the secret society Skull and Bones and friendships with fellow alumni (such as poet Phelps Putnam and painter Russell Cheney). The life of Knapp's wife, Helen Bayne Knapp, and her family are also documented in the papers.
Knapp, Farwell, 1893-1942
Knapp, Helen Bayne, b. 1896
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Helen Bayne Knapp (1967 and 1973) and Elizabeth Knapp Packard (2006).
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Farwell Knapp (1893-1942)
Farwell Knapp was born in Bridgeport, Connecticut, on November 28, 1893. He was educated at the Taft School (in Watertown) and Yale University where he was a member of Phi Beta Kappa and Skull and Bones. After his graduation from Yale in 1916 Knapp entered Harvard University Law School. Knapp left his studies in 1917 and enlisted in the Army, where he served with the 302nd Field Artillery in France. Knapp returned to law school after the war, graduating in 1921, and was admitted to the Connecticut Bar in 1922. The following year Knapp married Helen Bayne (1896-?) with whom he had two daughters (Emily Perkins and Elizabeth Cheney). Knapp first worked in the office of Shipman & Goodwin before he was appointed assistant tax commissioner of the state of Connecticut in 1925, a position he would hold until 1937, at which point he became a partner in the firm of Marsh, Stoddard & Day. In 1941 Knapp worked for a short time as a trust officer in the Phoenix State Bank & Trust Company before his retirement due to a heart condition. During his career Knapp also taught at the Hartford College of Law. Knapp committed suicide in 1942.
Scope and Contents
The Farwell Knapp Papers, consisting of correspondence, journals, photographs, and other papers, document the personal and professional life of Connecticut tax lawyer Farwell Knapp. Knapp's experience as a student at Yale University and Harvard University law school are recorded, including, for example, friendships with fellow alumni and his involvement with the secret society Skull and Bones. Farwell Knapp and his wife Helen Bayne Knapp's family life and friendships (including poet Phelps Putnam and painter Russell Cheney) are also represented in the papers. Knapp's journals contain entries on topics ranging from his everyday family life and health to philosophical ponderings and explicit details of sexual experiences. Knapp's career is also documented in both his own writings and contemporary publications that mention his legal cases.
Arrangement
The Farwell Knapp Papers is organized into the following four series: Correspondence, Journals, Professional Papers, and Personal Papers. Oversize material is listed at the end of the collection.
Books and reading; Childbirth -- Connecticut; Courtship -- Connecticut; Marriage -- Connecticut; Sex -- Connecticut; Diaries -- United States -- Connecticut; Photographs -- United States; Tax lawyers; Farwell Knapp journal; Bayne, Hugh Aiken, 1870-1954; Cheney, Russell, 1881-1945; Knapp, Farwell, 1893-1942; Knapp, Helen Bayne, b. 1896; Manning, Frederick J. (Frederick Johnson); Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1909-1975; Putnam, Phelps, 1894-1948; Stewart, Donald Ogden, 1894-1980; Harvard Law School -- Alumni and alumnae; Marsh, Stoddard & Day; Order of Skull & Bones; Phi Beta Kappa; Shipman & Goodman (Law firm); University of Connecticut. School of Law; Yale University -- Alumni and alumnae; Yale University; Yale College (1887- ). Class of 1916
- Correspondence, 1907-1947; Series I; 2.29; (6 boxes)
  Arrangement
  The series is organized into two subseries: Farwell Knapp Correspondence and Helen Bayne Knapp Correspondence. Within each subseries correspondence is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Some of Farwell Knapp's correspondence can also be found in his journals in Series II.
  Scope and Contents
  The series contains Farwell and Helen Knapp's personal correspondence dating from 1907 to 1947 and documents their relationships with family and friends.
  - Farwell Knapp Correspondence
    - "A" General, 1914-1929 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - "B" General, 1919-1942 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Bayne, Elizabeth, 1922-1941 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
    - Bayne, Emily, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Bayne, Hugh Aiken, 1923-1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Blodgett, William Henry, 1915-1942 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Bushnell, Sam, 1917-1923 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Butler, Nicholas, 1936-1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Includes Knapp's essay "The Nose of the Camel"
    - "C" General, 1915-1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Cheney, Lillian, 1923-1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Cheney, Russell, 1915-1942 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Cooley, Francis, 1915-1941 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
    - Cowles, Esther, 1923-1942 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Cowles, Knight, 1910-1940 (Box 1, Folder 17-18)
    - "D" General, 1916-1941 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - "F" General, 1923-1941 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Farwell, Frank, 1913-1923 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Farwell, Libby, 1915-1923 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - "G" General, 1914-1923 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Garrett & Co. Inc., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Geary, Donald, 1922-1923 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - General Electric, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Gross, Charles, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - "K" General, 1917-1922 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Kellogg, Freda, 1918-1919 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Knapp, Emily Hale Perkins, 1917-1940 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Knapp, Emily Perkins, 1939-1942 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Knapp, Helen Bayne, 1921-1926 (Box 2, Folder 32-33)
    - Knapp, Howard Hoyt, 1909-1917 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Kunhardt, George and Martha, 1910-1923 (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
    - "L" General, 1924-1940 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - "M-N" General, 1917-1940 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Manning, Frederick Johnson, 1920-1942 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Messina, Francesco, Count, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Military Emergency Board, 1914-1918 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Oler, Wesley M., 1915-1940 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - "P" General, 1918-1942 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Perkins, Lucy, 1914-1922 (Box 2, Folder 44-45)
    - Perkins, Thomas and Hafza, 1918-1923 (Box 2, Folder 46)
      Includes bookplates with Perkins coat of arms
    - Peters, Dorothy, 1916-1921 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Putnam, Phelps, 1918-1928 (Box 2, Folder 48-51)
      Related Archival Materials note
      See also: Putnam, Phelps
    - "R" General, 1939-1941 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - "S" General, 1917-1941 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Stewart, Donald, 1916-1941 (Box 2, Folder 54-55)
    - Swain, Robert, 1929, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - "T" General, 1915-1940 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Tener, Kinley J., 1916-1923, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Tighe, Hester Smith, 1919-1930 (Box 3, Folder 59-60)
    - Tighe, Laurence Gotzian, 1916-1939 (Box 3, Folder 61-62)
    - Underhill, Ednah, 1923, 1940 (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - "V-W" General, 1915-1941 (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Walker, Charles Rumford and Adelaide, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Wilson, Ralph, 1938-1939 (Box 3, Folder 66)
      Includes inventory of Knapp's collection of erotic literature
    - Yale University, 1914-1915, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - ----, Betsy, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Unidentified, 1915-1941 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Helen Bayne Knapp Correspondence
    - "A-Z" General, 1916-1942 (Box 4, Folder 70-72)
    - Bayne, Elizabeth, 1910-1925 (Box 4, Folder 73-77)
    - Bayne, Helen Cheney, 1907-1937 (Box 4, Folder 78-79)
    - Bayne, Hugh, 1913-1944 (Box 4, Folder 80-81)
    - Cheney, Lillian, 1912-1925 (Box 4, Folder 82-87)
    - Cheney, Russell, 1912-1931 (Box 4, Folder 88-89)
    - Cowles, Knight, 1918-1923 (Box 4, Folder 90)
    - Cowles, Tom, 1914-1917 (Box 4, Folder 91)
    - Fisher, Bob, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 92)
    - Jennings, Annie, 1937-1939 (Box 4, Folder 93)
    - Kitchell, Lloyd, 1923, undated (Box 4, Folder 94)
    - Putnam, Phelps, 1918-1947 (Box 5, Folder 95-116)
      Includes black and white photographs of Russell Cheney, Phelps Putnam, Helen Knapp, Farwell Knapp, and "Nina"
    - Putnam, Phelps, typed transcriptions, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 117-119)
      Transcriptions made by Helen Bayne Knapp of journals dating 1919-1947
    - Putnam, Phelps, typed transcriptions, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 120)
      Transcriptions made by Helen Bayne Knapp of correspondence between Phelps Putnam and the Knapps from 1922 to 1942. Include introduction by Helen Bayne Knapp who entitled the collection "Three Against Chance"
    - Smith, Edna Dow, undated (Box 6, Folder 121)
    - Stewart, Donald, 1921-1929 (Box 6, Folder 122)
    - Venner, Herman, 1919-1920 (Box 6, Folder 123)
    - ----, Charles, 1920-1923 (Box 6, Folder 124)
    - ----, Malcolm, 1921 (Box 6, Folder 125)
    - ----, Uncle [Minnie?], 1916 (Box 6, Folder 126)
    - Unidentified, 1914-1924 (Box 6, Folder 127)
  - Third Party Correspondence
    - Bayne, Hugh Aiken, 1913, 1937 (Box 6, Folder 128)
    - Putnam, Phelps to Elizabeth Bayne, 1918-1943 (Box 6, Folder 129-133)
    - Putnam, Phelps to Frederick Manning, typed transcripts, 1915-1939 (Box 6, Folder 134)
      Includes correspondence and poetry collected and transcribed by Helen Bayne Knapp in 1967
- Journals, 1907-1942; Series II; 4.38; (11 boxes)
  The journals are arranged in chronological order. Loose items were removed from the journals and placed in the folder following the journal or in Oversize (as noted).
  The series contains Farwell Knapp's journals written between 1907 and 1942. The series also includes two sets of typed excerpts from the journals made by Helen Bayne Knapp. In addition to journal entries the journals contain correspondence, ephemera, and black and white photographs of the Knapps as well as their family and friends.
  - Journals, 1907-1914 (Box 7, Folder 135-139)
  - Journal, 1914 (Box 8, Folder 140)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1914 (Box 8, Folder 141)
  - Journal, 1915 (Box 8, Folder 142)
  - Journal, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 143)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1916 (Box 8, Folder 144)
  - Journal, 1917 (Box 8, Folder 145)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1917
  - Journal, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 146)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 147)
  - Journals, 1918 (Box 9, Folder 148-149)
  - Journals, 1919 (Box 9, Folder 150-151)
  - Journal, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 152)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1920 (Box 10, Folder 153)
  - Journal, 1921 (Box 10, Folder 154)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1921 (Box 10, Folder 155)
  - Journal, 1921 (Box 10, Folder 156)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1921 (Box 10, Folder 157)
  - Journal, 1922 January - 1922 October (Box 11, Folder 158)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1922 January - 1922 October (Box 11, Folder 159)
  - Journal, 1922 October - 1923 Summer (Box 11, Folder 160)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1922 October - 1923 Summer (Box 11, Folder 161)
  - Journal, 1923 December - 1924 December (Box 12, Folder 162)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1923 December - 1924 December (Box 12, Folder 163)
  - Journal, 1924 December - 1925 June (Box 12, Folder 164)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1924 December - 1925 June (Box 12, Folder 165)
  - Journal, 1925 June - 1926 September (Box 13, Folder 166)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1925 June - 1926 September (Box 13, Folder 167)
  - Journal, 1926 October - 1927 October (Box 13, Folder 168)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1926 October - 1927 October (Box 13, Folder 169)
  - Journal, 1927 October -1928 December (Box 14, Folder 170)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1927 October -1928 December (Box 14, Folder 171)
  - Journal, 1928 December - 1929 March (Box 14, Folder 172)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1928 December - 1929 March (Box 14, Folder 173)
  - Journal, 1930 March - 1931 August (Box 15, Folder 174)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1930 March - 1931 August (Box 15, Folder 175)
  - Journal, 1931 August - 1932 December (Box 15, Folder 176)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1931 August - 1932 December (Box 15, Folder 177)
  - Journal, 1933 (Box 16, Folder 178)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1933 (Box 16, Folder 179)
  - Journal, 1939-1942 (Box 16, Folder 180)
  - Loose material removed from journal, 1939-1942 (Box 16, Folder 181)
  - Journal transcripts, undated (Box 16, Folder 182)
    Transcriptions of journals from 1907 to 1921
  - "Farwell Knapp Journal: Love Story of a Stoic Philosopher", 1967 (Box 17, Folder 183-189)
    Typed transcripts made by Helen Bayne Knapp of period between 1921 and 1923
- Professional Papers, 1920-1937; Series III; 0.42; (1 box)
  The series is arranged into two subseries: Writings and Other Papers. Writings are organized chronologically and Other Papers by last name of author and, when multiple or unknown authors, by title.
  The series contains writings by Knapp as well as other printed material relating to his professional life between 1920 and 1937.
  - Writings
    - "The Effect of Smith v. Loughman on Non-Resident Transfer Taxation", Connecticut Bar Journal, 1928 April (Box 18, Folder 190)
    - "Charitable Exemptions" and "Third Report of the Committee of the National Tax Association on Double Domicile in Inheritance Taxation", 1934, 1937 (Box 18, Folder 191)
    - Meeting notes, 1935, 1941 (Box 18, Folder 192)
  - Other Papers
    - Bigelow, E. Victor. "Mistakes of the Interchurch Steel Report", 1920 (Box 18, Folder 193)
    - Harvard Law School Class of 1921 Report, 1924 (Box 18, Folder 194)
    - Newspaper clipping regarding Knapp's employment with law firm Marsh, Stoddard & Day, 1937 (Box 18, Folder 195)
    - Perkins, Arthur. "History of an Old Law Firm Now Known as Perkins, Wells, Davis, and Schaefer of Hartford", 1930 (Box 18, Folder 196)
    - Supreme Court of Errors of the State of Connecticut, 1926-1931 (Box 18, Folder 197-198)
      Includes Farwell Knapp's cases
    - In the Supreme Court of the United States, 1927-1932 (Box 18, Folder 199)
- Personal Papers, 1891-1944; Series IV; 0.42; (1 box)
  The series is organized into three subseries: Financial Records, Legal Records, and Other Papers. The subseries are arranged alphabetically.
  This series contains personal papers of Farwell Knapp and Helen Bayne Knapp. The personal papers document financial and legal dealings, travel, and education.
  - Financial Records
    - Notes, 1939, undated (Box 19, Folder 200)
    - Receipts, 1917-1944 (Box 19, Folder 201)
    - Taxes, 1920-1936 (Box 19, Folder 202)
  - Legal Records
    - Passports and driver's licenses, 1921-1930 (Box 19, Folder 203)
    - Life insurance, 1944 (Box 19, Folder 204)
    - Lease and bond for deed, 1925, 1944 (Box 19, Folder 205)
    - Wills, 1937-1943 (Box 19, Folder 206-207)
  - Other papers
    - Journal fragments of Howard Hoyt Knapp, 1891-1925 (Box 19, Folder 208)
    - School papers, essays, and poetry, 1914-1915, undated (Box 19, Folder 209)
    - Harvard Law School first year examination, 1916-1917 (Box 19, Folder 210)
    - Certificates, 1918-1943 (Box 19, Folder 211)
    - Personal notes of Helen Bayne Knapp, 1922-1944 (Box 19, Folder 212)
    - Photographic postcard of Knapp, Odette Labourie, Mrs. Olive Squire, and STM, 1921 (Box 19, Folder 213)
    - Postcards of France, Italy, and Spain, undated (Box 19, Folder 214-216)
    - Souvenir booklet from Weathered Oak Herb Farm, 1939 (Box 19, Folder 217)
    - List of erotica, undated (Box 19, Folder 218)
- Oversize, 1.67; (1 box)
  - Loose items removed from journals (Series II), 1917-1942 (Box 20, Folder 219)
  - Taxes (Series IV), 1930-1936 (Box 20, Folder 220)